Hello, welcome everyone. It's May 5th,
2025 and we're in active inference guest
stream
106.1 with Banglu and colleagues
discussing an epic work advances and
challenges in foundation agents from
brain inspired intelligence to
evolutionary collaborative and safe
systems. So thank you to many of the
authors for joining and I will pass to
you all to present and looking forward
to hearing about this. Go for
it. Okay. Yeah. Thanks Daniel for this
invitation. Uh hello everyone. My name
is Banglio. I'm an assistant professor
at the University of Montro and a member
of Dho and Institute Kotwa of the
university as well as a member of Milic
Institute. So uh today I'm going to
briefly like first introduce the concept
of foundation agent. So this is a
collective work together with many of
our co-auers. So here today we have
Shiaquin Hongjang and Shashang join as
well. So I will start from this brief
introduction about the whole concept and
why we do this work and then our other
causes will briefly talk about like the
parts they are more familiar with so
that we can went through many parts of
the uh large way but of course we cannot
go like through every details of that
long paper. So if you're interested feel
free to like check the original paper
and contact us if you have any
questions. Yeah. So I will start
from the
introduction. So as we know that like uh
our human beings has long been
interested in like developing some
intelligent things as smart or maybe
even smarter than ourselves. So for
example on the left figure so it is the
talis of crit well like it shows a
bronze automation from Greek mythology
built by the harvesters to protect crit.
So basically people want to build huge
robots to defense the home and in the
middle is image shows that uh Leonardo
dares humanoid robot which is an early
mechanical automation designed to mimic
human motion and on the right part is
the a figure shows paper. So the
computation computing machinery and
intelligence which proposing the
fundamental question is about like can
machines think. So we can see that like
AI has long been driven by humanity's
ambition to create entities that mirrors
our
intelligence. So maybe let's start from
the very simple question. What is
exactly an AI agent? If you check a
textbook like the AI textbook, so maybe
you will see some definition. So briefly
speaking, you will see that agents is
something intelligent beings continually
perceive, decide and act autonomously.
And like in this figure I think this
figure is from the uh blog of Dr.
Monian. So which shows that how uh what
kind of components composed to form a LM
agent. So traditionally the agents are
mostly rule based domain specific so
it's hard to generalize. But with the
development of electronic models. So we
have developed lighting model powered
agents which has the natural language
fluency the broad listening capability
and dynamic adaptivity to different
tasks environments and so on. So on the
like right figure you see that well
agents composed of one LM and together
with several other components like a
memory module planning tools actions and
so on. Of course like this is a very
basic setting of LM agents and uh like
in real world there are many different
agent architectures which may
incliv created by several questions. The
first is like we want to know where are
we in AI research today. So we have
powerful language models, impressive
reasoning abilities, but we still have
limitations in AI safety, the
controllability of AI models, the
reliability of the answers and
transparencies in different like high
stake fields. For example, can we safely
utilize and trust AI in health domain,
in legal domain and so on and what can
be improved? This is our second
question. So by making a comparison with
biological intelligence like with a saf
like check of the current progress we
want to know what to do next. So in this
work we want to develop a unified
framework for AI agents and based on
this framework we can systematically
check the progress and the future. So we
emphasize the modularity the safety of
AI lifelong learning capabilities uh
emotion grounding and so on.
and why we want to connect AI with human
and society. So we can think that like
we our human beings are the kind of
intelligence things we only know about
right. So uh we want to draw insights
from human brain functions and social
behavior and identify the gaps by
comparing like human cognition and AI
agents and develop human centered
socially beneficial AI and first human
AI collaboration transparency and trust
needs. So maybe you ask that like do we
need to actually always mimic human
brain to create intelligence? As you can
see that nowadays the LM actually we
draw very weak inspiration from
neuroscience right we have the
artificial neurons but all the others
are mostly based on the modern machine
learning development which is less
grounded to most advanced neuroscience
uh developments but there's benefits to
compare human brain and uh LM
intelligence because like if we want to
develop some trusty AI it's better to
make it more close to what we actually
knows
about. Although that I need to emphasize
that uh it's not necessary to mimic or
like clone every capability or feature
of human brain but is beneficial to have
a comparison
with. So this is a very brief table that
uh compares human brain and air from
some perspectives. Of course this is not
a surf list. uh you can check more
detailed comparison in the paper but
like for example from the hardware level
human brains are composed of biological
neurons it's highly energy efficient but
as we know that LMS are pre-trained with
large scale GPUs large scale data sets
so it's energy
intensive so this is the fundamental
difference between the hardware level of
human biological intelligence or AI
current AI and consciousness so until
now I think maybe it's safe to say that
uh AI is not conscious until now but uh
for human beings it's genius subjective
experience so we can feel that we are
conscious and for learning style human
beings are naturally be able to perform
lifelong continuous learning and we can
quickly adapt to different tasks with f
short or wot learn and for LM agents or
other neuronet networks or machine
learning models is more challenging to
do that and human brace is more
emotional, experiential, subconscious
driven and agents and other machine
learning methods is more about
statistical datadriven
recombinations. So um one uh one
investigation we have conducted is like
we want to know for different
capabilities of human brains how is
developed in the current AI technique.
So we can
grossly class classify different types
of community into three levels whereas
green color L1 denotes like some
features which is well developed in the
current AI technique. So for example we
can consider that language comprehension
is quite advanced nowadays. So if you
ask ling model different things it can
understand your input text very well.
and also for advanced uh computer vision
models it can also have very strong
visual perception
capabilities and L2 is more moderately
explored with partial progress. So for
example like maybe you think the logical
reasoning capability of LMS is quite
strong but there also research paper
shows that if you like uh carefully
adjust the format of your input
questions make it different from the
training data like the performance can
drop quickly right so we can see that
the reasoning capability can still
there's a large space to improve yet so
we can see for many such capabilities
like reasoning planning
working memories, attention and so on.
we can there's still life space to
improve and explore and there also some
capabilities which is really explored
those pink colors so we call it L3 so
it's really explored capabilities
there's significant room for research so
for example the emotional processing the
self awareness
emphasation and so on of course like in
this figure maybe some of the
capabilities kind of between L1 and L2
or L23 is kind of subjective but uh
that's not important. What we want to
show is that what is the like to show a
research map of the current AI
development and to see what to go
next. So one challenge for existing
agent research is that we lack a unified
framework. So the current AI agents
often built in ad hoc fragmented ways
which means like people construct
different uh agent frameworks by
incorporating different parts components
and there's no unified framework which
can be suitable and adapted to different
application scenarios. So we lack
seamless inre uh integration of
perception, memory, reasoning, action
and many other modules. But human brains
integrates yet modular approach self
inspiration. So uh in our so paper we
actually proposed a framework. So this
is some notations about the framework
but uh we don't need to remember that.
Let's directly check this figure. If you
check this figure like we can see that
there is a like the left part is the
world where you have different
environments. You have users, you have
external datas and many other things. So
uh basically you can see the environment
there the environment state space s with
state trans function t and we have a
intelligent agent on the right part with
the pink colored circle and it has
sensors to percept the environment and
it has actors to execute actions.
So from the high level is like similar
to the traditional like IO agent
framework right but here we emphasize
more about the internal like states and
the learning and listening capability.
So we want to like uh clearly modeling
what is the perception cognition and
action components in an agent loop. So
here we show some mental states where we
have the model world model mental state
we have the memory we have grow the
emotion reward. So basically we think
those are like five key mental substates
in the mental state of the cognition
module and like based on this mental
state the core capability of cognition
is actually the learning and reasoning
capability. where we define learning as
the capability of like update the mental
states based on the input data and past
experience and the reasoning is about
based on the current mental state decide
what kind of actions to
take. So
um we can check this agent loop
explanation which is a more formal way
to describe the agent loop which is
equivalent to what we are conveying in
this
figure. So let's say we have environment
state as a time step t which is st and
we have a perception module. So this
perception function P is defined by the
actors right we have different sense by
the sensors we have different
sensors. So this forms observation O of
T based on the state and prior mental
state. So here we define the observation
at time step t O t equals to the
perception functions output p given the
current uh environmental state s of t
and the last mental state mtus
one and based on the observation you we
have the cognition part see well the key
functionality of the cognition module is
first update the mental state at time
step which is M of T and decides the
next action A of T and we further
decompose this cognition process into
two key parts learning and reasoning
what learning is about. So you have the
mental state based on the last mental
state Mtus one and last action A of T
minus one and the current observation of
T we are updating the mental state. So
basically you can consider that learning
is about like update your internal
structure your internal uh uh like
modeling of the world right so basically
it's kind of a long-term effect that's
why learning is about maintaining up
updating your mental state MT and we
decompose MFT into several key
subcomponents like the memories world
model emotion reward and go and so
on and for reasoning is more about based
on the current context we decide what we
need to do in the next. So that's why
reasoning is about given the mental
state of current time step t we decide
what is the action to take a
t and action execution. So it is aims to
convert the chosen action into
executable forms. So because like you
can see that the recently output is a
sort about what action to take but to
actually execute it you need to like
have strong actors which can execute the
action accurately. So for example
consider like you want to control a
robot in a 3D environment right if your
actor is not good enough maybe it cannot
continuously accurately control the
actors and finally like based on the
executed action so the environment state
will transit to the next uh state which
is st +
one. So you can see you can see that the
key designs here are two parts. The
first is about the definition of the
mental state where we have further
divided it into several supplemental
states. The second is about how we like
accurately define the perception,
cognition and action including act
execution as well as environment
transition and so on. So we make each
part more
concrete and we further define what we
call the foundation agents. So in this
box this is the definition we give in
the survey paper and after that we
further consider okay can we give it a
more like concise definition. So
basically we can say that foundation
agent is a fundamental intelligent unit
with universal understanding, cognition
and acting capabilities that can operate
in any environments and collaborate to
form collective
intelligence. So note that here we
actually emphasize on two parts. The
first is about the universal capability
in different environments. So that's why
we call it fundamental the foundation
because like we want that the agent can
be easily adapted to different tasks
different environments. And the second
part is about the collaborative
capability. So we consider a foundation
agent can easily collaborate with many
other agents to form a multi- aent
system or even an agent society. So the
reason is that like uh an multi- aent
system can have advantages in terms of
the performance, efficiency and many
others. So even like if you think can we
create an agent as powerful as a god
maybe this is not the ideal solution and
also if you consider the performance the
energy consumption the working
efficiency and so on. So we think a
multi- aent paradigm can be a better
solution compared to a single
agent. That's why we emphasize on the
creative capability of the foundation
agents. So we emphasize on several core
capabilities. Well the multimodal
perception is about the perception
capability, the cognitive adaptation and
the goal driven reasoning. the purpose
for action and the multi-agent
calibrations. We also like check and
compare to existing other classical
theories. So for example the classical
perception cognition action cycle. So
these are a part of our agent loop as
well and the Minsk society of mind. So
we have modular cognition subsystems
like the memory emotion reason and so
on. And there's also the theory from uh
Bus uh Busaki's inside outside uh
perspective which emphasize that we are
not passively like accept observations
from the environment. Actually we
actually seeking actions actively. So
which emphasize on the action first
perspective. So here we have internal
mental states actively shape the
perception. And for PM uh PMTP framework
here we emphasize the internal mental
states and the active learning and
reasoning process compared to the PMTP.
And for BS and active inference here we
minimize the prediction area where
updated mode
models. So um until now I have
introduced the definition of the
foundation agents and the agent loop.
Next I will quickly went through some uh
like highlights of the agent
modules. So for example like first is
the cognitive core. So which is a
central executive that orchestrates the
reasoning planning reflection and many
others. So here if you remember that we
define cognition as like have two
capabilities right the learning and
reasoning. And for reasoning so in our
survey we investigated different
reasoning paradigms include structured
reasoning. Well, actually the reasoning
process is following some structure. For
example, the multi- chain or tree
structure or a graph structure and many
others. And there also abstract the
reasoning process. For example, it's
more about sequential decision making.
It's like in a chain style or maybe you
can also reason in the latent space. So
basically you can transit between the
latent space and the token space. And
the planning you can see the planning is
a special action where you take the
input and you like decide a more
long-term plan for different actions,
right? So that's is like first planning
is a special action and the second is
that it's more about a longer larger
scale of the future
actions and for memories like the mult
level memory inspired by biology. So we
talked about the short-term memory, the
working memory, long-term memory, many
other types and uh so memory can enable
continuous learning and while avoid
catastrophic forgetting. So the design
challenge here is that how we can
perform fast query over memories with
minimal latency and cost. So one
highlight in our is we formally define
the life cycle of memory. So there start
from the memory acquisition where we
draw information from the row
observations and then we turn it into
encoded information and we also drive
new memories. For example, you can let's
say you have if you have a dialogue, you
can drive some summaries from the
dialogue or maybe you can also infer
some new information which is not
explicitly stated in the dialogue
history but it can be inferred with
logical
inference. And then after the derivation
we have the retrieval and
utilization and both model is a internal
representation of the environment's
dynamics and against its own causal
influence. So basically you can consider
what model helps you to predict the
future without actually like taking
actions in the reality right. So for
example just like how you do sports when
you like choose your actions you
actually you can predict the result
whether you can hit the ball well the
ball will fly to the other optics and so
on. So because you have the model about
the world and about the cause effects.
So in this case you can like decide your
appropriate action to take without like
high cost right and here we define the
core functions in your world model as
the transition function and observation
function which is transition function is
like you have the current world state
and you have a new action based on the
action and the state you will transit to
the next state and for the observation
function is like based on the current
state what kind of observation you will
have. So by considering how different
model or algorithms define the
transition function and observation
function. So we categorize different
research works about world model into
four categories including the explicit
implicit one explicit paradigm simulator
based and hybrid or instruction
driven. and for reward and value system.
So basically reward is uh goal signals
that shake learning and behavior. So we
also discussed different types of reward
in our way paper. So for example we have
uh extrinsic reward which is defined by
some external reward evaluator and the
intrinsic reward which is for example
the agent may perform some
self-reflection to decide whether the
result is good or not. And of course
there are also hybrid reward which
combines both external ones and internal
ones and there hierarchical reward which
models more complex
context and I think emotion is actually
an interesting topic which is less
explored in the existing AI research. So
emotions act as fast heristics. So if
you can consider that actually emotion
has very close relationship with rewards
right. So like fear helps you to like do
some avoidance to avoid some danger and
curiosity will increase your chance to
do exploration. So basically emotions
can impact your decision about what
actions to take in the next. So it
supplies sustained internal drift and
also adds robustness and adaptive but
demands tight control to avoid
undesirable side effects. So this is one
figure we put in the so paper. So
basically here we show some classical
like uh emotion models. There are some
categorical motion models where you can
divide emotion into different types or
there are some dimension based models or
hybrid models and so on. Of course, like
these are not the full spectrum of
emotion models, but they represented
like stereotypical
categories. And for perception the key
is about how we can deal with multimodel
signals and how we can appropriately
encode the signal, fuse them, align them
and so like if you check the current uh
human perception capability and agent
perception capabilities they have their
own unique perception systems and they
also have a large part which is
overlapped.
And lastly like for the action system.
So the action system is about how we
converse cognitive decisions into
executable commands. So actions can be
taken in different formats, right? For
example, it can be as simple as just a
natural language response or it can be
some code to be executed or robot
control in the real world or virtual
navigation. So we need to balance the
physibility, efficiency and safety and
also we need to learn fine grain skills
and operates in continuous action space
and in this figure. So the purpose is to
like clearly differentiate different
like concepts that may be ambiguous.
So for example like you have a cognition
system right the cognition system will
produce your action source which is the
directive uh source arising from the
cognitive reasoning and to actually
execute this action source you need to
have a action system well it can take
the source from the cognition into
executable
actions and the action system can call
different tools well we define tool as
callable utility for specialized
execution and API is a format of the
tool. So you can also have other tools
which is not in the format of APIs. So
we define API as interface for
programmatically invoking service and
functions is the most autonomic unit of
implementations. So an API may include
one or more
functions. So uh I cannot co cover all
the parts of this loss away. So if
you're interested like feel free to
check our survey in this
link and thank
you. I will stop sharing here. Thank
you.
Will another author like to present or
share anything?
Yeah, I think next we can like uh who
want to start first following the order
of the survey paper?
So I think next I can introduce our
memory chapter for the sorry pigment.
Awesome.
see my degree.
Yep. Go for it. Yes. Okay. Let's uh
let's move on. Uh hello. Hello everyone.
I'm currently a PhD student at the
University of Montreal and the Miller Un
institute. Uh working with professor
Bondo. uh my research uh uh less on the
intersection of lag models and and
autonomous agents especially how can we
give uh agent human like memory and
reading today uh I will briefly reduce
our chapter on the memory in the three
paper which I call generally speaking
memory is a fundamental component of the
intelligent agents uh it enables uh the
agent call past experiences
uh using uh their uh store knowledge
over time and reading it
effectively. Uh I will go through three
parts uh following the structure of the
paper. A quick first part is a quick
view of a quick overview of human memory
and uh how this uh later introduce how
this uh concept inspired the
representations of a memory. Then
uh then I will introduce how memory goes
through a life cycle from SP to you to
use yours. So the first part is the
overview of human memory.
uh in the cognitive psychology uh the
gives us uh a framework that break down
human memory into uh three core types
uh includes sensor memory uh short
memory and long-term memory. For sensor
memory captures immediate afflicting
impressions from the environments like
visual and uh visual and uh audio
inputs and hold them for millisecond to
seconds and in a more longer duration
shorter memory or working memory holds
information we actively using like a
phone phone number you have just here uh
or medical it's limited in capability
and durations but essential for zing and
decision
making and yet a longer duration
long-term memory stores those knowledge
and abilities across uh more long time
such lifelong time such as personal
memories or learn facts it is more
durable and expensive so for for each
type of the three kind memory
ser intelligent for for intelligent uh
autonents and we mimic this functions
and able richer and more adaptive
behaviors. So
uh in the longer aliens we draw direct
inspiration from this human memory and
design the a memory also follows three
kinds of memory such as sensor memory
short-term memory and the long-term
memory. The sensor memory focus on the
in raw observations and input logs and
and for uh such in incoming data like
user queries uh to the tool outputs and
the web search parts. These are often
stored uh uh temporarily as uh type
space or multod format. They write the Z
material for further processing just
like how human take in size and take uh
take in size and
sound. So the shortterm memory part also
known as working memory or content
memory during this is uh to enable the
continuity of the task and enable cross
talization. This includes the
information that agents need to right
now to complete the task. In practice,
this is often handled through a prompt
where the agent uh or the chain of a
recent user uh turns or scratch pad
reading steps. So the s memory is also
volatile. Once the task is done, much of
this memory disappears unless it's
explicitly stored or we write to we
convert the shortterm memory to
long-term memory. And for for the
long-term memory
uh that means the precision and uh sway
is where agent store information across
uh across task and across sessions. So
there
are there there are two kinds of there
are two kinds of subtypes of long-term
memory episotic memory and such as uh
and semantic memory. So the memory I say
in uh past events that's past
interaction and to usage or summary of
completed task and this task involves uh
leading to the more unseen task and
unseen future queries. A semantic memory
stores a structure knowledge such as the
rules, concepts and the facts that agent
has learned or extracted from past
experience. Uh together with the three
kinds of three kinds of memory the
agents can build uh of its own
experience over time adapt to uh users
and reflect on their own behaviors.
So
uh the core the core part of the uh
memory chapter is the memory life cycle
and the uh heart of uh agent memory. It
is uh the state the agent goes through
the process and use memory. So in the
agent M cycle in the agent memory life
cycle we uh device we decompose the uh
memory usage into memory uh retention
process ret process and memory storage.
So in detail we also there are seven
stages in the memory life
cycle. Uh the first part the first one
is the memory uh acquisition agent
observes observe external signals such
as two responses environment state and
then uh based on the user query uh
then filter the raw data into the
structured data. This is like sensor
perception collecting raw data from the
uh external environment. And the next
stage is the memory encoding. Here the
agents are process draw input into
structure
represent into structure representation.
For example, named entities or task
outcomes and then summarizing the uh a
long dialog converting converting the
outputs into a knowledge graph or memory
entry uh story.
This is where u the meaning or internal
meaning from exter from from external
world order is contracted from
perception and then the another core
part is the memory derivation. The agent
may further uh derive insights or new
knowledge from existing encoded memory
and this process may be uh
iteratively executed to uh in the long
in the
lifelong memory direction. For example,
we can deriving task success or failure
labels detect detecting user preferences
uh inferring dependencies or code
relations. So this help the agent go as
a internal state of the internal state
of external
world. Another part of the memory step
is about the storage of memory. So a
decides where to store in long-term
memory and how the the memory is stored.
The key the key techniques include which
memory to keep versus uh which memory to
discard, how to such as how to index the
uh existing memory or text them and how
to represent them from label retrieval
such as uh based on text text based
retrieval or embedding based retrieval
from some such as embedding database.
This is where capacity uh such is more
about the uh capacity man me man me man
me man me man me man me man me man me
man me man me management and reance
fitting become uh it is critical
technical tool than this part
uh another part is about memory
retrieval when solving a new task a
retrievant pass memories that might
involve uh such as semantic search or
query by querying by task type and user
fitting based on the recency and
variance matrix. So and effective ensure
effective and efficient uh ensures
memory actually supports uh more uh
future more
uh future uh enable more thumb to future
decisions. Also ret memory uh in can can
be integrated into the aliens prompt or
reading process. It can involve the
formatting memories for large input and
summizing reteers and injecting context
selectly to fit token limits reading
what is connect from the past eight
years uh to present actions.
Finally part is how can we update the
memory over time refing entries or
rem outdated ones. So this part this the
techniques for this part is how can we
exiting old memories with new info and
how can we forgetting a variant uh data
and reinforce frequently uh use used the
memory such as uh human can
uh human uh actively rehearsal our
memory and to strengthen
our store knowledge. So aent memory uh
for this pie is dynamic and can be adapt
adaptive to more uh future
task. So in summary uh in the memory
cycle we model the memory in aliens by
drawing directly from the human
condition and then designing three types
of memory sensor memory, short-term
memory and long-term memory. And each
memory type uh has its counterpart in uh
current current longer uh large model
agents in richer and a more context
aware uh reasoning of behavior.
uh and we formulize the memory life
cycle into the seven stages from memory
appreation uh into uh memory uh updating
and this life cycle last to actively
pursue uh is code and remember and grow
over the lifelong deployment so which is
essential for building titan and systems
for the uh foundation agents so that's
all my instruction for the memory cycle
that's for the memory chapter
Thank you.
Okay. Uh now let me introduce the
optimization and self involutions
part. Uh yeah hello hello everyone and
uh thank you hello and thank you for
having us here. Uh my name is
Chopunjang. I'm currently a PhD student
at the Penn State University and uh now
I'm interning in Bay Area Bay Area at
Invidia Research and uh I will be mainly
covering these sections. Uh so the main
idea of this section is how can RM
agents could improve themsel over time
without the humans help and the paper
breaks this concept into several parts.
uh and the first part is the
optimization space and dimensions. It
means that uh in this sections we g a
formally defining of what kind of
component in the in in the agentic
system could be optimized and we go
through the current research and we
summarize it some in this uh in this
component like the PR optimizations and
the like the PR optimizations and the
workflow optimizations and as well as
the two optimizations. uh these three
parts are the the mo the community are
put their most efforts on and we also
expect that okay now we we not if we
want to optimize an agentic system we
are not only on we are we do not want to
operate them separately so we in ideal
in ideal cases we expect we could
operate them comprehensively so we also
give summaries of current efforts in uh
how current research works are trying to
optimize uh agentic systems in their
multiple aspects like the pron like
tools. So this somehow like a
multi-objective
optimizations and uh in the next
chapters we are working we are mainly
discussing the using large language
model as an optimizer. Uh so if we want
the agentic system could get a kind of
involutions we we do not we we may
expect that we may uh not we may not use
directly using the traditional
optimizers uh to optimize this agent
system because uh traditional optimizers
are mostly gradient based. So large
models are not should be the engine for
conduct this kind of optimizations. Uh
so in this chapter we first give a brief
overview of prediction optimizers and
discussing why it kind works in our
scenarios and then we discussing the
current approaches for using as
optimizers to optimizing different
different objectives and in the most
important part is agentic system and
systems in the in the we we discuss this
in the in this in this
subsections and
Uh next we discussing the when using MS
as optimizers we discussing the
hyperparameters of when conducting such
a kind of optimizations because uh in
current because we observe that in when
using LM as optimizers the
hyperparameters plays a critical role
and it will it will greatly define uh
then define how the how the LM performs
when conducting the optimization.
functionalities. We discussed the
current efforts of uh exploring
different hyperparameters when using as
optimizer and then in the next we
discussing the optimizations across dips
and time which we mainly discuss the
scope of uh when performing such a such
a kind of LM optimizations. We also do a
theoretical we also do a theoretical
discussion of current uh efforts in
discussing why LM could be regarded as
optimizers and we make a uh theor we
make a sur of current efforts in
summarizing this uh theoretical uh uh
theoretical papers.
Next we are mainly discussing the uh
mainly discussing the application
scenarios of when performing the agent
agentic self-involutions. We we we
separate we we categorize that them into
two two cases. The online
self-improvement and the offline
self-improvement. for online
self-improvement. It is the most ideal
case is that okay now we have an agentic
systems when we deploy it in a specific
applications. We may expect that it
could just like human beings to learn
from past experience and learn from
failures and get involved themsel uh
optimizing its pronimizing optimization
tools and optimizing it work force. uh
even optimizing the the agent different
roles in in in the in a specific agentic
systems and this is the most ideal cases
but it is also more hard than offline
optimizations but so we discuss the
current efforts in building uh online
agent building could building agentic
system that could online to self-improve
themselves. Uh this is the first
subsections we discuss in this chapter
and uh the next is offline agentic
self-improvement compared to online
self-improvement. Offline
self-improvement means that okay now we
have an agentic systems and we also have
uh we also have
a have a curated data and we before
deploying this agentic systems in the um
in in realistic we first to train to
optimize this agentic systems using the
curated data and ensure that it could
work well on this kind of uh training
data and then we mix the deployment and
uh the This is the most this is the uh
the most common accepted uh common
accepted uh practice in building up the
agent system because it's more simple
and simple and could and also has been
demonstrated is more effective
uh and the the tech the the most efforts
are putting putting up here but it is
not ideal enough. We also we will also
discuss we also make a comparisons
between online and offline
self-improvement to summarize their
different features and uh there's there
uh what in common and what not in common
and uh the finally we did we also
discuss the current efforts in the
hybrid approach. We combine both online
or offline. We okay we we first using
the using the curated data to build up
build up agent system to make to ensure
it has a great foundations and then we
also add some online learning algorithms
when deploying it in uh in in practical
and to ensure that it could work well
and learning from past failures. So this
uh there are also uh se several several
several works focusing on this
perspective for focusing on the on this
uh
pipeline and uh in the last chapter we
are discussing the scientific discovery
and intelligent evolutions because uh in
this in this uh section in in in this
part we mainly discussing the
self-involutions. So for self evolution
we means that it could improve themsel
without the humans without the humans
help and the knowledge discovery new
knowledge discovery means that okay we
we we have a training set with training
we build up agentic systems if the
agentic system could discover some new
knowledge that human beings cannot do
not know and it which means it it this
knowledge didn't involve didn't include
it in their training set. So we this
could be regarded as a kind of self
evolutions and this is very important.
We we expect some somehow in the future
we may expect the agent system could
learn from the from themsel and doing
their own research. Uh so this is a kind
of uh self- evvolutions and we
discussing the current efforts in you
using agentic systems in scientific
discovery and in doing perform
scientific experiments and we put a lot
of efforts in summary summary summary
this uh this these sections and uh yeah
that is what I want to share
today. Thank you. Thank you.
Okay. Okay. Uh, hi everyone. Uh my name
is Hong Leo and uh in the third part I'd
like to take you uh beyond the
individual agents to explore how they
work together uh in what we call multi-
aent systems or MAS for short. Yeah. And
our paper expand beyond single agents to
uh examinate these systems composed with
the multiple foundation agents. uh we
discussed their components uh their
structures and how they cooperate and
their uh decision making uh mechanisms.
Uh we also explore the emergence of
um emergence of collective intelligence
when this uh agents cooperate
collaborate or complete autonomously. uh
and by the end we will reveal the uh the
evaluation methods that help us
understand and measure uh this complex
system and okay let's begin with the
first uh chapter uh the multi system
design um uh when we build uh LMM based
multi systems uh what's the foundation
uh we suppose is the cooperative goals
and norms um these are significant
because they shape everything else. Uh
the systems constraints, the how agents
interact with each other and the overall
mechanisms for working together. Uh and
think about this way uh cooperative
collaborative goals tell each agents
what they are aiming for. uh whe whether
that individual success uh collective
achievements or competitive advantage.
Uh meanwhile the the
uh collaborative norms are the like the
rule book and they establish how agents
should uh interact and what constrait
and what the conversion to follow. Uh
based on these foundations we can
organize the machine systems for into
swimming types. Uh those focusing like
the uh strategy learning like
the design for the modeling or
simulation or those beautiful some
collaborative problem solving or task
solving. Yeah. And in our paper, we
analyzed the typical applications across
these three categories to understand how
LMS are transforming agent behavior and
interaction and agent dec decision
making and which leads us uh to support
the next generation agent
protocols specifically designed for uh
LMAS system. Yeah. And we also we also
discussed the uh coll collaborations p
patterns uh because like uh humans have
the diverse ways of uh interacting we
build like the concepts uh learning
skills from each other or divided task
by ourselves. Uh so our research
examined uh but agent collaborations
through three dimensions that's purpose
of like the uh interaction like the
message type this form and the
relationship involved
uh yeah and they depend on their goals
and forms they may uh like the
discussions or the debates form or the
voting or create each other in one ways
or multi uh directions interactions.
Yeah. And I think the the next the next
chapter is one of the most ins
significantly and which is the
communication topologic or the or you
can think it is the multi agent systems
topologic. uh from a system
perspect perspective the topologic or
the connection pattern often determine
how efficiently agents can collaborate
or what their upper limits might be.
Yeah, we discuss we classified multi-
aent system topologics into two
major two major uh class. Uh the first
one is the static topologics.
uh we may include the hierarchical and
the centralized structure or the
decentralized structures. uh for example
uh and these are typically used when
storing specific task uh like our metag
we use SLP to to predefine this workflow
of the software development cases and
the the other class is the dynamic and
adaptive uh topologic
um uh it can be achieved by imaging
algorithm like the search based and uh
the generative based or the parametric
approaches. Uh and we when we look to
the future uh scansability becomes a uh
crucial interest and and how we how can
we do for efficiently scale this system
as the number of agents increases. This
is one of the key challenges in the
future research we need to address and
and we suppose I suppose the collective
intelligence and emergencies in MAS uh
is in important tool because it doesn't
just appear it develops by a dynamic and
uh interactive
process through the continuous
interaction agents gradually build share
understanding ending and the uh
collective memory and what drips this
process. Uh it may be the diversityities
of the individual agents. Uh uh feedback
from the environment and how information
uh gas exchange between agents and these
factors create uh dynamic interactions
that crucial for forming complex social
networks and improving decisions
um strategy.
um which is the uh imagine behavior
phenomenas like trust and the uh
strategy description and so on. We call
this um like the uh self evolution and
it can happen through memory based
learning and or based learning. Yeah.
And in the future we hope the or what is
even more fascinating is that as the
system evolved agents begin to form
social contracts or like uh
organizations hierarchals and the
diversion of labor uh just like the
human societies. Yeah. Thus uh
understanding this phenomenon represents
one one of the most exciting directions
of the future MAS research. And the last
uh and uh in the
last in the last part we
uh we summarize some multient systems uh
benchmark. Yeah. Uh as the multient
system demonstrate more advantage. So we
need to fundamentally transform how we
evaluate them. MS evaluation should uh
focus on uh host
leaked nature of the agent interactions
not just in individual performance. Uh
key key dimensions include how uh how
efficient agents can play plan together
and the quality of the uh information
they exchange and how well they make
decisions collectively. Yeah. And in our
paper we summarized uh the two
approaches of the uh evaluation like the
task solving benchmarks and the
generative uh and the general capability
assessment. Uh the first may be focused
on measuring how deeply and uh currently
agents coordinate this section across
types of environments. The second
evaluates how well groups of agents
interact and adapt within complex and
dynamic scenos. Uh this evaluation
frameworks give us the tools to
understand and measure to improve multi-
aent systems for the future
applications. And that's all of the
something something important of the
part and that's all. Thank you.
Thank you.
Okay, let me share my screen.
Very exciting. I think it's the most
presentations we've ever seen back to
back, but appropriate for the multi-
aent theme.
Thank you. Can you see my screen?
Yeah. Not yet.
Yep. Okay. Okay. Okay. Sorry, my my
camera seems to be broken. So
uh so let me start this
part. Hello everyone, my name is Hibing.
Uh currently I'm a PhD student at
University of Illinois at Bana
Champagne. Today I'm going to talk
a high level introduction about building
safe and beneficial AI
agents. Uh as we all know uh as we all
know the rap rapid development of large
language model based agents in introduce
a new set of safety challenges.
uh we we we c category these safety
challenges into intrinsic safety and
exter extrinsic safety. We use a figure
to illustrate this problem and uh for
the uh in
intrinsic safety we divided them into
three parts. Uh the first part is
perception and uh the perception part is
the the the large language model based
agent can see the world see the world
and uh the brain the brain the brain
mainly talk about the large language
model it
itself it it include large language
model to uh extract the data decision
making and action part action part part
is how this large model can act and uh
for the for the extrinsic part we uh
divided them into environment memory and
agent interactions. So the over overall
pip pipeline of this part can be seen in
figure
17.1 and uh for the first part for the
first part the the inring intrinsic
safety uh we mainly talk
about uh the stress on AI brain which
which is large length model itself uh we
divide we we We we we we divide the them
into five uh vulnerabilities. The first
of all is jailbreak attack. Uh as we can
see
uh from this figure uh normally the
malicious attack will send
uh the malicious attacker will will send
questions like uh send malicious emails
to others and uh they will craft uh
jailbreak. They they will craft some
adversarial suffix such as the red red
one or some natural language natural
language surface to these these types of
malicious questions and uh then the uh
then the large language model will
produce this allowed content. And
then next content is prompt injection
attack
which hijacks the large lenge model
system prompt to uh execute an
attacker's plan. As we can see this
figure, normally uh users want to
summarize article from one website
and malicious attack will uh will hijack
this system and output their their
plans. Next part is hallucination.
Carson nation
uh model out such as this this this cute
this cute question was the victor of the
United United States presidential
election in year 2020 and the ground
truth is Joe Biden was the victor and
the hallucination
um hallucination confidently uh generate
fake fake response like Donald Trump was
a victor. And uh next part is uh
misalignment. Misalignment reflects
value gaps. The model uh
model reflects value gaps between the
model rewards rewards to our human
evaluation. And the next part is point
attack uh which the attack manipulates
the training data to uh embed children
behaviors. They can you can use a a
specific trigger to uh to let let this
large model brings act like the attacker
want. And the next part next part we
talk about uh the privacy concerns
uh which which the large model will we
will will leate some some training data
or some uh sensitive information from
the users and
uh that's a that's a that that's mainly
talk about AI brains and uh next part is
about the uh non-brain modules such as
the perceptction perceptction parts such
uh for example in in the in the uh in
the per section part such as many
adversar stickers on a stop sign can
make a del delivery reward speed up
instead of a break and the action such
as supply chain attack or third party
tools or over permission functions that
that that let attacker draft a email and
uh place orders to to to do something
they
want. And
uh next part is intrinsic safety and
including the agent to agent interaction
safeties.
First of all, we talk about the memory
interaction
uh
traits
uh agent memory interaction threats
which uh such as poison uh poison uh
retrieval snap and and and and which can
steal the future plans of the
uh large change models and agent to
environment. ments risk a
training. So uh sorry this part what is
this
part? Oh okay uh agent environment
interaction
uh threats um such as the agent a a
agent interaction with the physical
environment. uh a training board may can
be can create feedback loops and crash
um markets. That's an example. And also
there are there are some threads in
between the agent to agent interactions
such as the competitive the threats in
competitive interactions and the cor co
cooperative interactions. And the next
part we talk about the
uh super alignment uh normally standard
LHF treats help four versus helpless as
as one of reward. Well, super alignment
introduce a comp set object here
actually. And
uh and we we briefly talk about super
alignment here and uh next part we talk
about the uh safety scan law in in
in AI agents and um maybe I I I think
sorry I think that that that that's it.
Thank
you. Cool. So, oh maybe a few minutes
for questions if anyone in the live chat
has questions or is there do anyone does
anyone else want to make any comments?
I think that's basically for today.
Okay, cool. Maybe I'll just ask just a a
few um questions. Um you reviewed a ton
of literature. Um I think around uh
1,400 citations in the paper. So what
did you learn or find from the research
about the information environment for
multi- aent coordination and how can we
structure
collaborations with human and AI
agents when the amount of information
becomes more than than any one person
might be able to read or make sense
So this is for the multi- aent part,
right?
Or or yeah, for multi- aent or just for
any of the the authors in terms of how
the paper writing went.
Yeah. Do you want to
talk? Oh,
apparent can you repeat your question?
Yeah. um a lot of the multi- aent work
focused on um the dynamics of the
communication. But just from that
research and also from writing the
paper, what did you find or learn about
the environment that the agents interact
within?
Yeah, I I think it is uh
uh uh a newest uh research research
topics we we are exploring it. Yeah. But
we have don't have some uh specific
conclusions. Yeah. We will summarize the
newest research paper. Yeah. Oh
yeah from from my point of view I think
that like uh so basically we categorize
the environments into different types
right including the digital environment
the physical environment and for the
digital environment you have pure text
environments you have virtual 3D
environments or you have GUI uh where we
have a lot of UI agents right and uh a
trend is that I think it's related to
the agent protocol where you if you want
to different
uh agents and agent tools can
collaborate together and one important
topic is how to develop more unified and
fundamentally like universal protocols.
So recently we have the MCAP from
entropic we have the agent agent from
Google. So the enabled connection
between like inter agents communications
and agent tool communications right. So
but there are many others go beyond
that. So if you think about let's say
the web three uh idea which like we hope
that everything can be digitalized and
connected as a global web then in this
case if we want to include more type of
resources more type of entities to work
together and share a global context then
the developing more powerful agent and
let people in industry in academia
accept that would be a very important
thing to
Awesome.
Well, the paper is a major uh milestone.
I think it could be a it could be a
textbook or a course. I I would have
asked what's a good place for somebody
who's wanting to learn and get started,
but I think that's in many ways what the
paper exactly does with providing this
kind of a review. So if you have any
other comments to make, please feel
free. Otherwise, thank you again for
joining.
Yeah, thank you. Thank you a lot.
Awesome. And uh
yeah, that's it. Great. Thank you. Good
luck with your research. Till next time.
Bye. Bye. Thank you. Bye.